<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true believer's testimony of the work of true faith; who hath believed in Christ Jesus the true light, who enlighteneth every one that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe. Wherein are many excellent things held forth, which through faith in the light are seen, learned, and certainly believed, &amp;c. and are profitable for all to reade. With a visitation to the called of God every-where. By a servant of the Lord, Geo. Rofe</title>
            <author>Rofe, George, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222733</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833873</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833873</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38351</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38351)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2214:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true believer's testimony of the work of true faith; who hath believed in Christ Jesus the true light, who enlighteneth every one that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe. Wherein are many excellent things held forth, which through faith in the light are seen, learned, and certainly believed, &amp;c. and are profitable for all to reade. With a visitation to the called of God every-where. By a servant of the Lord, Geo. Rofe</title>
                  <author>Rofe, George, d. 1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Rob. Wilson, in Martins le Grand, near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Note - The fore part of this pamphlet, 'A True Believer's Testimony, &amp;c.' was written in Virginia, and 'A visitation, &amp;c.' in Maryland." -- cf. Smith.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38351:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38351:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE BELIEVER'S Teſtimony Of the WORK of True Faith; Who hath believed in CHRIST JESUS the True LIGHT, <hi>Who Enlighteneth every One that cometh into the World,</hi> that all men through Him might believe.</p>
            <p>Wherein are many Excellent things held forth, which through <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Light</hi> are ſeen, learned, and certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and are profitable for all to reade.</p>
            <p>With a Viſitation to the Called of God every-where.</p>
            <p>By a Servant of the Lord, <hi>Geo. Rofe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Rob. Wilſon,</hi> in <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins le Grand,</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38351:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38351:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHoſoever thou art that ſhalt reade this little Book, Be it known unto thee, that I have not given it forth in any deſire to appear unto men to be a ſetter forth of Books; but in the Innocency and ſimplicity of my heart, as it was upon me from the Lord, who moved me thereunto by his own Spirit and Power, elſe I ſhould not have ſet my Pen to Paper, to appear in Print; So if thou readeſt in Innocency and ſimplicity of heart, thou mayeſt ſee that my End is, to manifest the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Truth of God, and to eſtabliſh many in the Faith; which if thou truly deſireſt after, then have regard to the Light, which Chriſt hath enlightned thee withal, that thou mayeſt reade with a ſound Mind, and a good Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, weighing and conſidering ſeriouſly as thou readeſt (and not making light of it) and then thou mayeſt come to underſtand thoſe things which thou never underſtoodst, and to ſee the Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, who is the true Light and Truth, by which we are carried through Nations, and upheld in all Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both by Sea and by Land, having the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb facs="tcp:38351:3"/>of an <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom;</hi> after which we earneſtly preſs, and labour to bring People to; for which ſake all the Kingdoms of the World are againſt us: But we do aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly believe, That the Truth ſhall overcome them: And though we have nothing on our parts, but the Truth of our God to uphold us againſt all our Enemies, (who are as the ſtars of Heaven in multitude) yet they ſhall fall, and dye away, and waſte as the Dew, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mouth ſhall be ſtop'd, and every Power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, which riſeth up againſt us, and the Truth of our God in which we live, and in which we have believed: which if thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt to believe in, fear not, though thou maiſt meet with Difficulties, but believe in the Truth and true Light, and thy Faith ſhall give the Victory, Farewel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. R.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38351:3"/>
            <head>A True Believer's <hi>TESTIMONY</hi> of the Work of True <hi>FAITH, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AFter that from my Childhood, I had often both deſired, and ſought after the Lord, in <hi>ſighs</hi> and <hi>groanings,</hi> and many <hi>tears;</hi> and ſtrong <hi>cryings,</hi> the Lord in his own time, manifeſted Himſelf to me, by the Light which enlightens every one that comes into the World, that all through it might believe; in which Light I came to ſee my ſelf when I firſt believed in it: and when I firſt came to hear it ſpeak in my heart, and to own it, I came to hear the Word, by which Faith comes, for it prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Faith unto me; and by Faith in it I came to ſee all that ever I did, and to have all my ſins brought into my remembrance, and ſet in order before me, by the Light, which comes from Chriſt the Author of Faith, who enlighteneth every one that cometh into the World, that all through Him might believe.</p>
            <p>By Faith in the Light I came to ſee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38351:4"/>Judgement kindled in my heart, and the thoughts, and intents and purpoſes of my heart <hi>revealed,</hi> and to own the Judgments of God upon all that ever I did, and that God was Juſt, Holy and True in all His Wayes, and in all his Judgments.</p>
            <p>By Faith in the Light I came to ſee, if I forſook not the vain courſe of life in which I lived, the Wrath and Judgments of God abode upon me.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee how all the world live in wickedneſs, and ignorant of the true God, not knowing the way of Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee all the World With its Ways and Worſhips, are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, they acting all they do, in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and with that ſpirit and mind, which tranſgreſſeth and is without the Faith, and out of the Light; and that which is out of the Faith &amp; out of the Light cannot pleaſe God, for out of the Faith none can pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee where the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Man's ſoul lodgeth, and how he dwells in the hearts of all Tranſgreſſors, to turn the purpoſes of every heart unto Evil, and to corrupt the thoughts of every mind.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38351:4"/>
            <p>By Faith in the Light I came to ſee the Judgment of the World, and the Prince of the World judged and caſt out.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee the Seed which is immortal, which through Faith it hath pleaſed the Father to reveal in me, and Thouſands of his Sons &amp; Daughters, which by Faith he raiſed from the dead, through his own Spirit, which makes us to differ from all the World.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee the Image of <hi>God</hi> renewed in his Seed, which Seed is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> one in the <hi>male,</hi> and one in the <hi>female,</hi> who is the Lamb of God, which was ſlain from the Foundation of the World, which God is raiſing in many Sons and Daughters, to work out that nature which hath tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the Sins may be taken away, and the Tranſgreſſions blotted out.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee, that no one is in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> nor in the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> which is Life Eternal, who are not come to believe in the <hi>Light,</hi> and to witneſs the Word of Faith in the heart and in the mouth, to give them Victory over every evil Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, every evil Luſt, every evil Deſire, every evil Thought and Word, which the <hi>Light</hi> checks and reproves for.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38351:5"/>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee, that it is the true <hi>Light,</hi> which enlightens every one that comes into the World, which mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts every ones evil, and reproves the evil of every heart, and checks for every evil word, work, thought and deed, and that this Light is ſpiritual and eternal, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver changeth, but is the ſame; though when man or woman changes their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it changeth its Adminiſtration; it preacheth the Goſpel truly in them, even the Day of the Vengeance of God, to that which tranſgreſſes; and Peace, Love and Good-will to every one that obeyeth and worketh Righteouſneſs, both to the <hi>Jew,</hi> and likewiſe to the <hi>Gentile,</hi> without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting or accepting any perſon, but wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the Truth in all, as in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee that the <hi>Light</hi> which enlightneth every one (that all men through it might believe) is the very <hi>ground</hi> of the knowledge of all <hi>Good,</hi> and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the very <hi>Life</hi> of God it ſelf, in which his Seed is known, in which God hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> not only to <hi>live ever,</hi> but that all that believe in it <hi>might live by it: Becauſe I live, therefore I will that ye live
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38351:5"/>alſo.</hi> And this is the <hi>Promiſe</hi> in the Seed, before the World began, even <hi>Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> which in the Saints abides, when the World ſhall be no more; who through Faith have overcome the World and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Life Eternal, and this is <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>only true God</hi> and the Saviour of the World, who is from Generation to Generation.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to ſee, that the Light which enlightneth every one which comes into the World, anſwereth the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and is the Life of them both, condemning every Tranſgreſſor &amp; Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; in which Light, the Law being manifeſt, condemneth the <hi>Jew</hi> that hath the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſinneth under it; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the <hi>Gentile,</hi> who having not the <hi>Law</hi> in the <hi>letter,</hi> ſins out of it; and by the Light all the World will become guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that every tongue may confeſs to God, and every mouth may be ſtopped, when by the <hi>Light</hi> (which enlightens every one) every ones deeds will be manifeſt; for that records them all in the Book of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and brings them all into remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance before God, and teſtifieth of them between God and man, ſo that all come to be left without excuſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38351:6"/>
            <p>By Faith in the Light it's given me to ſee how all the World live in vanity, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the <hi>Light,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and thoſe things that are noted in the Scriptures of Truth; and it's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they have more ſet at nought, and leſs eſteemed on, and leſs regarded than theſe, and leſs regarded than the Lord and his Truth, and the Scriptures (or writings) of it, though ſo highly cried up in words.</p>
            <p>By Faith I ſee, they prefer even thoſe things which are as naught, and worſe than naught (for they corrupt their minds) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Truth and Scriptures of it, even in thoſe things in which they tranſgreſs the Apoſtle's Doctrine, in following the faſhions of the World, in wearing of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Pearls,</hi> and <hi>coſtly things,</hi> and <hi>Rings</hi> on their <hi>hands,</hi> and <hi>Jewels</hi> in their <hi>ears,</hi> and <hi>Ribbonds, Toys, Baubles,</hi> and <hi>coſtly Laces</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> on all parts of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, according as the luſts of Ignorance, and the treachery of the proud, earthly Nature, and earthly ſenſual Wit, invents Faſhions, to the great Diſhonour of God, and their own Bodies in which they ſhould bear the Image of God, and ſanctifie their Veſſels unto Honour: but alas! the Body
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38351:6"/>which ſhould be for the Lord, that is given up to be fornicated after thoſe unprofitable things before-mentioned, and many more in the Faſhions of the World, in which many have given up themſelves; and in vain Bowings, and vain Complements, and vain Traditions, and vain Flatteries; and though they will ſay their hearts are not in thoſe things, yet by Faith in the <hi>Light</hi> I have ſeen long ago, That all who live in ſuch things, and ſay their hearts are not in them, deceive their own ſouls: for, by Faith I have ſeen long ago, that none can live in ſuch things, but they do it to pleaſe that which is vain and of the Vanity, and out of the Spirit of the Truth.</p>
            <p>By Faith I have ſeen, that it is hard for many to let the World go; for many hang in it until they become ready to paſs away, and periſh with it: But bleſſed are they whoſe part is in the World to come, who have denied themſelves and this World, and let the Kingdom of this World go; whoſe part is in that which is Immortal.</p>
            <p>By Faith I have ſeen that none can come highly to eſteem of the Truth, and the Scriptures of it, but who believe in the Light, that by Faith they may deny the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38351:7"/>World, and all things thereof, and their own ſelves alſo; for that which loveth the World, the Wrath of God is upon it, the Love of the Pather is not in it; this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the Father and the Son, and highly eſteems of the Scriptures, and never comes to <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay</hi> in all Communications, neither fulfilleth the <hi>Royal Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets;</hi> for this is ſelfiſh, and lightly eſteems of, the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and will not fulfil them, in doing to all men as men would be done unto.</p>
            <p>By Faith I ſee this Principle which is earthly, and hangs in the earthly Nature, is a ſnare to thouſands in this the Day of the Lord; and earthly things are ready to enſnare many, when they by Faith have overcome many other things, which were ſnares unto them before: but bleſſed are all they that dwell in the Faith, in the Light, in the Power which gives Victory over the World, and over all that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains unto it. <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World</hi> (ſaith Chriſt:) <hi>He that will enter into my Kingdom, he muſt deny himſelf, and take up his daily croſs, and follow me: for none can enjoy two Kingdoms, nor ſerve two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:38351:7"/>
            <p>By Faith in God I received Power to deny my ſelf, and to croſs my ſelf in the love of all things, and all delights beneath the Truth of God, and to lay hold on the hope of Salvation, though for its ſake I ſuffered with the reſt of the flock of God in the <hi>hatred</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> in <hi>Reproaches,</hi> in <hi>Stonings,</hi> in <hi>Tumultings,</hi> in <hi>Scourgings,</hi> in <hi>Stocks,</hi> in <hi>Priſons,</hi> in <hi>Fetters of Iron,</hi> in <hi>Brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,</hi> in <hi>Woundings,</hi> in <hi>Travels,</hi> in <hi>Rejection of all the World;</hi> and yet by Faith have <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced</hi> over them all in hope, accounting all things as nothing to be compared with the Glory which God hath revealed in his own Seed, and the Power which by his own Son he hath revealed in me.</p>
            <p>By Faith it was confirmed unto me, that the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt's</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Writings, the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> are certainly Truth declared from the Lord, and the Words of the moſt High God, which I never doubted on from a Child, but that they were to be believed by all.</p>
            <p>By Faith I came to receive an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in thoſe things noted in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth, and to be ſatisfied concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things therein contained; for in the day when I ſought Knowledge, and was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38351:8"/>ready to be incumbred in ſeeking out the myſtery of things by Faith in the Light, I received the Anſwer of God, which I read in the word of Faith in my heart, which ſpake on this wiſe, faying, That I needed not to ſeek Knowledge, but to wait upon the Lord, and to have my mind truly bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before Him in the meaſure of his Life, and whatſoever thing I ſtood in need of to know, and that the Lord ſaw it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, He would certainly give me the knowledge of it, and to underſtand it in the Lord's own appointed time: VVhich Word hath been as a Stay to my Soul, and I have ſeen God fulfilling it from day to day, who hath made known Himſelf to me, and given me His Truth; who requireth nothing of any one under Heaven but that which He firſt giveth; who condemneth none but for diſobeying that which He giveth.</p>
            <p>By Faith I ſee all the Profeſſors of the World are aiming at the <hi>wrong Mark,</hi> and ſeeking the <hi>wrong thing,</hi> and in the <hi>wrong Way;</hi> for they are ſeeking after <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and to grow <hi>high</hi> in <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of words,</hi> when as they ſhould ſeek after the <hi>Life,</hi> and wait for the <hi>Power</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38351:8"/>God, which ſhould lead them in pure <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to the Lord and to his Truth; which <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> if they miſs on, they will be but as if they had precious Ointment of the Apothecary, but, alas, Flies have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted it, that it cannot cure: Even ſo, if all the knowledge of the World whilſt mixt with earthlineſs and enmity, neither doth it ſtand in the Power of the Lord, which redeemeth out of the World, and giveth to ſeek after God, and feel after Him, in his Life to walk in his pure living way, which who come into, ſhall not want Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom nor Knowledge, but ſhall have it in the gift of God.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's given me to ſee that the ſame Life which God hath in theſe laſt dayes made manifeſt, and declared to be the Light of the World, and doth enlighten every one that cometh into the VVorld, was in the dayes of Old; which is the Heart of God, by which he purpoſeth and upholdeth all things; which Life in due time was declared to be his Son, and made known in the Church while in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and was the Rock which followed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of which they drank, when they were joyned unto the Law, and baptized
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38351:9"/>into <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea: by which <hi>Moſes</hi> He was ſeen, that God would raiſe Him up in the midſt of the People, for all the People to hear, that he that would not hear Him might be cut off: So that certain it is, the Law did propheſie that the Son of God ſhould come; and not only ſo, for he was manifeſt in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> preaching to the Spirits in Priſon, whoſe day <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw and was glad; by which Life the Prophets wrote of his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, which they ſaw and witneſſed, (ſhould certainly be fulfilled) before the Seed was raiſed up through the Virgin, which Seed is <hi>Chriſt</hi> who is come, and hath taken the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and ſuffered in the body, which Sufferings by Faith in the Light (which He hath enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened every one withal) are clearly ſeen and believed, to be done and fulfilled ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures; So that by Faith in the Light it's ſeen, and certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that the Lord's Chriſt is come in the fleſh, hath ſuffered and is ariſen in Glory in the Kingdom of his Father, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuffered and fulfilled all things that was written of Him, being declared by ſigns and wonders and mighty deeds, to be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38351:9"/>the only begotten Son of the Father, the Prince of all his Saints, the Kings of the Earth and Prieſts unto God; and all theſe things hath he done and ſuffered, as it was written of Him in the Prophets, <hi>That He being the firſt-born among many Brethren, and the firſt begotten from the dead, might have the preheminence, being in all things a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and Example in all Godlineſs and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, humbling Himſelf unto death, even the death of His Croſs; that in all things</hi> (He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Example) <hi>we may follow Him in His Sufferings and Death; who in that He dyed once, dyed unto Sin, in that He liveth, He liveth unto God, Death hath no more domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over Him.</hi> So likewiſe is every one, dying unto Sin, to live unto God, that the reſidue of the dayes may be ſpent in the Service of God, and the death which hath reigned in the mortal body, and ſubjected the Creature unto Vanity, may have no more dominion, but may be ſwallowed up and conſumed unto the end in the Victory of the Judgments of the Life.</p>
            <p>And by Faith it is ſeen that it is a greater Myſtery <hi>to know Chriſt</hi> to be the <hi>firſt-born,</hi> who muſt be witneſſed <hi>born</hi> firſt <hi>in Man,</hi> before Man can be <hi>born again;</hi> and be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38351:10"/>from the dead, before Man can be begotten from the dead: He that reads, let him underſtand; he that reads, muſt read by Faith in the Light: and bleſſed is he that readeth, and heareth, and ſeeth, and hath part in theſe things; he ſhall give Glory to the Lord, and to his Chriſt, who is tranſlating many Sons and Daughters out of the Kingdoms of this VVorld into Himſelf, and into His Kingdom, to praiſe and glorifie and magnifie Him for ever.</p>
            <p>By Faith it is ſeen that Chriſt is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted to be that which was written of Him, namely, to be a Covenant of the People, and Light of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Ends of the Earth, who is able to ſave to the <hi>utmoſt</hi> all that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by Him; who hath freely offered up himſelf once for all, and by the one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified; and not only ſo, but being an Atonement for Sin, hath appeaſed the Wrath of God towards all, ſo that He is become a Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World, having obtained Favour with God; ſo that time and ſpace is given, and a day of Viſitation unto all; that the Long-ſufferings of God waiteth towards
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38351:10"/>all: And this is the Liberty and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; which Chriſt through his Death and Sufferings hath purchaſed for <hi>All,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> Men having a Viſitation, and time, they might <hi>Repent</hi> and turn to the Lord, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Righteouſneſs; which, if they neglect their time, and through impudence and impenitence and hardneſs of heart, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in their ſins and unbelief, and ſo <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath, and the revelation of the Righteous Judgments of God;</hi> ſuch ſhall certainly periſh, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>greater Condemnation,</hi> when the meaſure of their <hi>Iniquities</hi> are <hi>full;</hi> and all the Sufferings of Chriſt will be laid to their charge, who have pierced the Juſt, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Grace and the Light, which from the Juſt is come, to witneſs againſt all Tranſgreſſion, and doth teſtifie againſt it in every ones Conſcience: and this all ſhall ſee to be true, that the Sufferings of Chriſt, will be but to the <hi>greater Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of them that continue in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though by <hi>His ſtripes</hi> are they <hi>made whole</hi> who turn unto Him: but the Juſt when He appears, the Families and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of the Earth ſhall weep and waile over Him, when every Eye ſhall ſee Him,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38351:11"/>and them that <hi>pierced</hi> Him <hi>ſhall behold</hi> him; for He ſhall come in the <hi>Glory</hi> of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and in the <hi>Power</hi> of his Father, to ſit as Judge upon all the Families and Kindreds of the Earth, pleading with them by Sword and Fire, and righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, taking Vengeance on all who have not wrought Righteouſneſs on the Earth, nor walked prudently amongſt Men, to ſhew forth his Praiſe, and the glory of his Grace, in obeying unto an <hi>Holy Life</hi> and <hi>Pure Converſation:</hi> and as he comes, riſes and appears, He deſtroyes the ſpirits of <hi>Belial,</hi> and conſumes the Tranſgreſſor, that His Covenant of Peace and Life for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more may be eſtabliſhed with and in His Seed in which He comes, and in which he reveals himſelf in the Children of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, in Mighty Power, that his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence may go along with them and his Arm may defend them, and his Glory follow after them to be their Re-reward: And the Spirits and Life of all the Children of the Promiſe, the Heirs of Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion He upholds, who give themſelves up unto Him and to the Appearing of his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Light of His glorious Goſpel which ſhines in their hearts, that they may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38351:11"/>be unto Him as the Tower of <hi>Sion</hi> and the Bulwarks of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> in them hath the Star ariſen which hath ſhined from the North, and is broken forth in the Darkneſs of the Night, and is ſhining towards the South, it riſes in the Eaſt, it looks towards the Weſt, and there is no place for its go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down: The Lord hath Multitudes of People, He gathers them as the Bands of the Earth, He ſuffers the Nations to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them for a ſeaſon, He chaſtizeth with the Rods of Men, that He may prove them all for His Glory: And yet a little while and the Rage of the Heathen ſhall ſink: He correcteth his People for their Good, and chaſtizeth them for their Peace-ſake, that He may build up his Nation which He hath viſited, and eſtabliſh his Seed which he hath gathered, and multiply his People: <hi>Thy Throne O God, endures for ever, and the Scepter of thy Righteouſneſs; who letteſt not Sufferings and Tryals to come upon the Seed which thou hath choſen, and the People which thou haſt viſited, to deſtroy them, but to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them; that when thou haſt tryed them as Gold, they may be eſtabliſhed, and fitted for thy uſe: that they may be humbled and all fear before thee, and wait upon thee, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38351:12"/>thou mayeſt renew us all from day to day, and night after night, in thy Life, to do thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, to fit all thine to Glory and Praiſe, and Honour immortal; for thy great Name thou art ſpreading over all the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Faith it was given me to ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Worſhip of the true God conſiſteth, and how He muſt be worſhipped in the Spirit and in the Truth, which the Father ſeeks ſuch to worſhip him, as worſhip Him in the Spirit, as worſhip Him in the Truth, and in the true Light, which enlighteneth every one; in which none can ſee the VVorſhip, but who come into the Faith, and into the Humility, and into the Fear, and into the Waiting, and into the Zeal for God, which bows the heart before God; and the heart being bowed, then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration is come into, and the Inquirings into the Knowledge of Life, and the ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to feel the Spirit which brings the Truth into Remembrance, and alſo brings to be ſtill and quiet, and wait in ſtilneſs and quietneſs, and ſilence; then God is ſeen and felt, and his Life which gives the Creature to feel after God, who comes to be felt in his Life which enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth the Creature, and gives the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38351:12"/>livelineſs to wait for the renewing the ſtrength, and God reveals his Word, his Power and his Requirings in the Creature which works in the heart and in the reins, and runs through the mortal body, and is weighty in operation, to give Power and Dominion to the Creature, to the end that it may have full power and ſtrength to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Aſſaults of the Devil, and to have its mind ſtaid in ſtilneſs and quietneſs, and ſilence and waiting for the Love and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Mercies of God; which being felt, then the Lord is admired and bowed unto: this is VVorſhip, to bow before the God of Heaven, that all that's in Man may be bowed down, and ſubmitted under the Life and Power, then he worſhips, he boweth down to the higher Power, his ſoul abhors all defilements, his thoughts are ſtaid on God, his heart is kept tender and open, and he is refreſhed in the Enjoyment of the Life, and of the feeling of the Preſence of the Lord and of his Power, by which the Creature comes to admire the infinite Love and Mercies of God, and the Riches of his Grace, that after ſo long living in diſobedience the Lord ſhould reveal his Power, and make known the Riches of his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38351:13"/>Grace to ſuch a Creature that hath been as altogether unworthy; but the Lord hath done it for his Seeds ſake in Man, which never conſented to, or took pleaſure in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but hungred and thirſted after God, and breathed after God, and moved in the Creature towards the Lord, even while the Creature was yet ſubject to vanity; and for the Seeds ſake the Lord is merciful, full of compaſſion, long-ſuffering, and ſlow to Anger; and bleſſed are all they that turn unto Him in the obedience of His Seed, and in the Faith of His Son, they ſhall ſee his Mercies, know his Preſence, feel his Life, Power and Spirit, which bows and brings to worſhip God.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen that none are more ſenſible of the feeling of the Preſence of the Lord, than when they are ſtill and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and wait in ſilence and ſtilneſs, even when met together, and when alone: for, by Faith many are come to ſee, that the Lord is very near, and that they feel his Preſence when they wait upon Him, and his Life breaks forth in his tender Love, to the great refreſhing of the ſoul, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Creature; this takes away wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs and leanneſs from the ſoul, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38351:13"/>the multitude of vain Thoughts which have lodged in Man; ſo, that though they may often appear, yet they become ſtilled as though they were not; for when any thing appears contrary to the Will of God, the Light is near and ready to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Judgment upon it, and to give the Creature to apply its mind to Judgment, through which God redeems out of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances, and reveals his Noble Spirit of Life, which ſtills the Thoughts, and the Deſires and Affections which would raiſe Luſt and War in the fleſh; ſo that Man comes to wait out of himſelf, and out of his own thoughts and imaginations, in the Life, the Promiſe it ſelf, where it feels the Riches of the Love, and of the Mercies and of the Grace, and of the Power, which brings into the Glory, and into the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Life and Love, where the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal body becomes filled with Immortality and Life, which ſwallows up mortality in Victory, and Conqueſt, and Dominion, and the delight of all mortal fading things: and this hath made me bold and confident in the <hi>Lord</hi> of my <hi>Life,</hi> to give up my whole ſtrength for the witneſſing forth the Truth through Faith (which by Faith is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38351:14"/>of God) even through the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by Sea and by Land, as the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, which I account Eternal Salvation, though for it I ſuffer many things: but all is good, and for good.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen how exceeding good it is to wait upon the Lord, and to be ſtill and ſilent before Him, and in all things to eye Him and fear Him, then the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances come to be taken away, and the Darkneſs and Doubtings diſſolved, and Courage and Boldneſs for God received; which gives to fulfil his Will, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Peace, and to get Conqueſt over all the Enemies of the Soul in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; and this gives Peace in all the World, and ſatisfieth concerning outward things, and enjoyments, and gives to ſee the end of them all; and that the loſſe of Eſtates, Friends, Relations, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the outward body; all is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and but a parting with that, which muſt be parted with, be it ſooner or later, the Will of the Lord be done; for, we praiſe God, we have found Chriſt, and all things elſe is but as dung and droſſe, and muſt be parted withal.</p>
            <p>By Faith in the <hi>Light</hi> man comes to ſee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38351:14"/>Him that is inviſible, and to the end of all viſible things and delights, and to be made willing to let all the Honours, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments and Riches of the World, and the Great Name and Reputation to paſſe away, as that in which Life is not to be found, and to be ſatisfied; if he loſes any thing for the Lord's ſake, and the Goſpels ſake, he ſhall receive his Reward.</p>
            <p>By Faith it comes to be ſeen that every one having <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Rayment, they are therewith to be content;</hi> and that the labour of all, in the works of the Creation, is to be for the Glory of God, and for the Praiſe of God, and the Honour of God; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones Labour is to be for the <hi>Lord,</hi> and not to incumber themſelves, with taking care to lay up in ſtore for Generations to come, and for a Son or a Daughter, which its not known, whether they may glorifie God therewith or no; ſo that every one in his preſent Generation is to preach Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in all things, that in all his works he may preach for God. <hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of Righteouſneſs obtained mercy with the <hi>Lord</hi> in his Generation, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed God, even God that hath created Heaven and Earth, and all that lives there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38351:15"/>who watereth the Earth with the dew of Heaven, and cauſeth it to fall upon the tender Graſs, ſo that it buddeth; and to mollifie the Clods of the Earth, that the Seed yeeldeth encreaſe, <hi>Seed for the Sower and Bread for the Eater;</hi> who ſatisfieth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very living thing that hath life and breath, both in Heaven and in Earth, and in the Waters under the Earth, ſo that upon Him the care of every creature is to be ſet, and the expectation of every Creature is to wait upon Him; who is the Provider for all Generations, from Generation to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, unto a Thouſand Generations; that his Works might be ſeen unto all, and the Wonders of his Mercies throughout all Generations, to the ſetting forth of his Praiſe unto all Generations, that the works of his Hands might all praiſe Him, and He might be extolled by all his Creatures: But certainly Generations have abuſed themſelves, and diſhonoured the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; and the Enemy of Mankind hath had his ſtrong-holds in bewitching thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands and ten thouſands to ſet their hearts on earthly things, and earthly delights, more than God; ſo that they have forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten God their Saviour, &amp; rebelled againſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38351:15"/>the Rock of the whole World, who hath founded the Sea and the dry Land in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and every Creature in his Power; who reſerves the Wicked in his Wrath, and places them in His Diſpleaſure unto perpetual Generations. And indeed this is the ground of the ſnares of all the world, the Enemy having bewitched the minds of People, to delight themſelves in earthly things, they have forgotten God their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and defiled themſelves with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and with the reſt of the Creatures; having their thoughts tempted to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, they give themſelves up to be earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carnally minded, and to have the burnings of the luſts to run into the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and height of glorying in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and this is that which ſeparates the families of the Earth from God, and which cauſes the enmity, and the warrings, and envyings, and diſcord in all the World, againſt which the Law it ſelf was given; for in that Nature which delights as before ſtands the ſum of the Tranſgreſſion of the Law, from which a man muſt be born and redeemed, before he can love the Lord with all his heart, and mind and ſoul, and ſerve Him with all his ſtrength; and to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38351:16"/>love his Neighbour as himſelf; and to do unto every one, as he would be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; which fulfills all the Law: but the Earth is the Snare, and the parting with it the fear of many, and the keeping many from the Covenant; though man, in giving all things up to the Will of the Lord (and himſelf too) gives but the Lord's Own to Him, which the Lord requires, that in all things He may be ſerved and honoured; and who gives not up freely, the fear with which they feared the Lord will bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and the thing which they put far off He will bring near and make them ſuffer in: Therefore ye Families of the Earth, if you will come to the Covenant of God, give up to the Lord in all things, whoſe right it is, and ſhake your ſelves; come out of the love of the World, and the delights of thoſe things in which thouſands have periſhed, that Satan may not tempt you; for when you are tempted, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and defiled, you have firſt let your thoughts out to take pleaſure or liking, and to love that (or thoſe things) at which the Temptation pointeth, elſe you could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo eaſily overcome, as to make Sin the greateſt pleaſure in the World: for, if
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38351:16"/>you believed in the <hi>Light,</hi> and walked in the <hi>Light,</hi> in the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and in <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> you would ſee the Thoughts, and judge them, and not ſuffer the Eye of the Mind to look on that at which the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation pointeth, to take delight in that, and to love that, and to advantage thy ſelf in that; and then the Tempter ſhould not overcome thee, neither wouldſt thou like the Glory of the World, though tempted to it: This is the great Temptation, which bleſſed is he that overcometh, and getteth the Victory through the <hi>Faith,</hi> by which <hi>Faith Abraham</hi> forſook his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's houſe and native Country, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred a Pilgrim and a ſtranger in a ſtrange Land, ſeeking a habitation, which was not an <hi>Earthly Tabernacle,</hi> but <hi>Eternal in the Heavens, whoſe Builder and Maker was God.</hi> By which <hi>Faith, Moſes choſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Affliction with the People of God, rather than to enjoy the Pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon;</hi> and would not dwell in the King's Court, nor be called the Son of <hi>Pharoah's</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. By which <hi>Faith</hi> the Saints choſe to <hi>wander in Sheep-skins and Goat-skins,</hi> and <hi>in Dens &amp; Caves of the Earth; ſuffering the ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their Goods with joy; giving up their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38351:17"/>Bodies to ſuffer all manner of Tortur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s:</hi> theſe overcame the great Temptation, and <hi>loved not their Lives unto Death: Of whom the world was not worthy; who through then faith ſuffered all things, not accepting of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:</hi> By which <hi>Faith</hi> many in this Age give themſelves up in the like Sufferings, having the Evidence of a better Kingdom than that of this World; counting all things as nothing <hi>that we may win Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Light</hi> the Covenant of God is ſeen, and the Spirit of Life recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the heart, to be a Guide and a Ruler; which writes its Law in the heart, and puts it in the mind, in which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the whole courſe of a Man's Life and Converſation comes to be read, as Man comes to take heed unto the Grace which brings the Salvation and ſaves the Soul, and the Creature daily from the ſnares of the Devil, in teaching the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>that denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, they may live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent evil world,</hi> and ſo come to know the Promiſe of the Covenant ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in them, which ſaith, <hi>That all the People of God ſhall be taught of God,</hi> and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> far from <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38351:17"/>which none comes to witneſs but who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves in the Light, the Grace which chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the heart; for ſaid God, <hi>I will make them a new heart, and give unto them a right Spirit, that they may have all One heart, and all One way, and ſerve me all the dayes of their life without fear:</hi> Which none comes to witneſs, but ſuch as believe in the Light, and wait in the Light to feel the Fountain of Life and Power opened in them, to <hi>waſh them from Sin and from Tranſgreſſion,</hi> as the Lord ſaid; for, if this be not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, the Iniquities will oppreſs the Soul, and defile the Creature, and the old trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill abide, which will make the nature treacherous, and yield its mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, members of obedience unto Sin, and ſo to tranſgreſs the Law, and ſo to be in hatred of God; and this keeps from know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Anointing of the Soul with the Power of the Higheſt, which teacheth all things; that <hi>the Saints need no man to teach them, but the Anointing in them teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them all things which are Truth, and of it is no Lye;</hi> and this Anointing in them gives them to know the Father and the Son, and to have an underſtanding to know all things, both of the <hi>Law</hi> and of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:38351:18"/>that they need no man to bid them, Know the Lord; for the Seed of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is in them, the Heir of Life, by which they ſee the Lord teaching them all; ſo that <hi>All know Him, from the leaſt to the greateſt,</hi> and are <hi>All taught of Him,</hi> and <hi>have ceaſed from man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils</hi>) and <hi>love Him, and keep His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> which to them are not <hi>grievous,</hi> but <hi>joyous,</hi> though for their Obedience they may ſuffer, and have ſuffered by the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in Bodies and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>By Faith it is ſeen how Chriſt is a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>unto the utmoſt of all that come unto God by Him,</hi> who in His firſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ring in the Creature manifeſts ſin, and condemns for ſin, who being believed in, deſtroyes the ſin, and works that nature out of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which hath ſinned and taken pleaſure in ſinning, and ſo gives the pardon of the ſins paſt, and gives the Creature to live in obedience in the time to come, and ſo manifeſts Himſelf to be a Saviour to the Ends of the Earth, and that <hi>He is mighty to ſave, and to redeem his People out of all Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Fleſh und Spirit, that He may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them in himſelf without ſpot or wrinckle,</hi> or any ſuch thing, <hi>an Holy Church, a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38351:18"/>Houſe, builded of living ſtones, an Holy Nation, a Peculiar People, a Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, ſeparated from ſinners, and zealous of good works.</hi> And thus through Faith Chriſt comes to be ſeen to be a <hi>whole Saviour,</hi> and that the ſame Life in which He manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Himſelf in the Creature, which ſaves from <hi>Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Whoredom, Theft,</hi> and the like groſs evils, is as able to root out the very ground of the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion as it is believed in, and to deſtroy the earthly nature which hath finned; and to ſave from all ſin, and make man wholly a right Seed, that <hi>he may be perfect, as his Father in Heaven is perfect and holy;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is holy, without which Holineſs <hi>no man can ſee God;</hi> neither can any out of the birth of the Holy Life ſee the Kingdom which the Children of the Covenant ſee, and are Heirs of, being born again, <hi>not of corruptible ſeed, but of the Word of God, which lives and endures for ever;</hi> by which Birth they keep themſelves that the wicked one toucheth them not: And this is the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the World, which tramples upon the World, and all its Delights and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hions and Vanities, and hath put a croſs and ſtop to that in them, which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:38351:19"/>was of the World; and <hi>he that is born of God ſinneth not, neither can he, becauſe the Seed of God is in him,</hi> which keeps him from ſinning, and gives him to deny the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Devil, which would draw to ſin; and in this are the Children of God and the children of the Devil manifeſt; <hi>he that doth Righteouſneſs is Righteous, even as God is Righteous;</hi> he that ſins is of the Devil, and hath neither ſeen God, nor known Him.</p>
            <p>By Faith in the Light it is ſeen, that none can ever come to know the ſecrets of God, but ſuch as believe in the Light which hath enlightened every one that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the World: And there's not any that can ever come to be true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, true Miniſters, true Teachers, true Apoſtles, true Elders, true Paſtors, true Evangeliſts, but ſuch as believe in the <hi>true Light which enlightens every one that comes into the World;</hi> for he that believes not in the Light, he is not Zealous for God's Name, and for his Truth and his Glory, and againſt all the wicked World, and its wayes: And he that is not zealous for God, he is dark, the World is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his heart, he ſinks under the wicked, and wants the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38351:19"/>true diſcerning Spirit, which ſhould warm him with Power and Zeal, and ſo wants the true Diſcerning, and the Openings, and the Revelations, Viſions and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and the true Knowledge of Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which the Nations are to be turned unto, ſuch cannot be Miniſters of the Riches of God under any name, nor do the work of God aright; for he that doth Gods work aright, muſt have it ſo wrought in him, that he may do all things according to the Pattern that he ſees of God; And he that is not zealous for God, he receives not the true Wiſdom, he cannot be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, but muſt be propheſied againſt: he that is not zealous for God, he hath not the Viſion of God, nor the Revelations; he cannot be a Teacher to open the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God, but muſt firſt have Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment opened in himſelf: He that is not zealous for God, and againſt all the World and its Deceit, he cannot be an Apoſtle, or a Paſtor; he cannot feed the Sheep and Lambs, but muſt firſt be fed with the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God himſelf to bring him off the Earthly-mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dneſs, in which he feeds, and off th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ghts of the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men, after which his eye looks and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38351:20"/>his heart ſavours and would take pleaſure in: He that is not zealous for God, he cannot be an Elder, he cannot watch over Souls, but ſuffers the luſts in his own fleſh to lead him captive: be that is not zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for God, is no Evangeliſt, no ſetter forth of the Myſtery of the Kingdom: he that is not zealous for God, and againſt all the World, he cannot be a true Miniſter of God, nor become worthy to receive the hidden Wiſdom, and the Riches of the Power which opens the eye, and ſeals the Inſtructions in the heart: He that is not zealous for God, and for his Truth and his Righteouſneſs, he cannot get the Victory over the World, and over the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Error of his Life, to crucifie his earthly nature and mind; but his mind will be earthly, and corrupted with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in, and loving that, in which the ſeed of evil doers delights; he will be taken in the captivity of the Enemy, and in the Snare, and in the Cloud of Errors, and fall into Adverſity, which he cannot eſcape: He that is not zealous for God, cannot love God with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heart, but will reaſon with fleſh and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d about earthly things, and the ſufferings of this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38351:20"/>life, and will love ſomething better than Chriſt, and ſo be unworthy to do his Will, and to enter into his Kingdom; and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give up all things, ſuffer all things, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all things for Chriſt's ſake: He that is not zealous for God, cannot work the Works of Eternal Life, nor do the Work of God uprightly, only for the Lord's ſake, and in love to Him, looking for no other reward but the Lord; which work the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles, and Miniſters of God and Chriſt did through <hi>Faith,</hi> though <hi>contrary</hi> to the World, and its Teachers and Ways; though for it they ſuffered many things, yet by <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Light</hi> they were upheld.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it's ſeen how juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Joſeph</hi> was, who though he was ſold into Adverſity, and to be a Slave, yet ſtood faithful unto the Lord, even in the Land of his Captivity, and would not hearken to the Entiſememts of a Whoriſh woman, though never ſo ſecretly, but rather choſe to give up his Life and his Body unto Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Priſons, than to tranſgreſs the Law of his God; who through Faith gave up to ſuffer, rather than to enter into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements; and his Faith brought him through the Sufferings, and to be faithful in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38351:21"/>
               <hi>Ten</hi> Temptations; ſo that by his Faith he ſubdued the whole Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> under himſelf, and became Lord of it all; who was as a fruitful Vine upon the Wall, and his Branches reached unto Heaven; who for his faithfulneſs was greatly beloved of God, and made a Ruler over the ſons of men.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen how zealous <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant of the Lord was, who, as a Servant, was faithful in all his Houſe, who did the work of God uprightly; who (when through Faith he had forſaken <hi>Pharoah's</hi> Court, and refuſed to be called the ſon of <hi>Pharoah's</hi> daughter) ſought to ſet up Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice in the Earth, and to eſtabliſh Truth and Righteouſneſs amongſt men; who though he was rejected by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, men, yet God made him a Judge and a Leader of his People, and to appear before <hi>Pharoah,</hi> to bring his People out of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; who refuſed to lead them out on <hi>Pharoah's</hi> terms, but would have them go freely with all they had; and he bowed not to the will of <hi>Phareah,</hi> though <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> oppreſſed the People the more.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it's ſeen when <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his Task-maſters oppreſſed the Seed of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:38351:21"/>moſt, they (to wit, <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) were neareſt Deſtruction; for the Lord heard their Cry of Oppreſſion, and delivered them, and overthrew King <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> and all his Hoſt.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen and believed, that it was juſt in <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſanctifie the People in the Wilderneſs (after he had brought them to ſtand ſtill to ſee their deliverance out of <hi>Egpt</hi>) though wicked men withſtood him, and ſaid he took too much upon him; and <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> gathered a Company againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, who, with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, periſhed in their <hi>Gain-ſayings;</hi> for the Earth opened her mouth and ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them up quick, and many feared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their Cry. This is a true Figure to all Earthly minds, whoſe Cry will be great, who are ſwallowing up in the mouth of the Earth, and ſo goes down to their home quick, becauſe they withſtand the Sanctification, and do not believe they ſhall be cleanſed and perfected in this life.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that it was juſt with God to plague <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs, becauſe they followed not the Lord fully,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38351:22"/>though He was unto them <hi>a Cloud by day,</hi> and a <hi>Pillar of Fire by nighty,</hi> (to preſerve them from the Heat and the Cold, and to guide them in the way wherein they ſhould walk. You may underſtand ſomething by this, if you read in the Light) but went into Fornication, and luſted after things that were not convenient, and looked back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> to luſt after the <hi>Fleſh-Pots</hi> of <hi>Egypt;</hi> who <hi>ate and drank, and roſe up to Play, every one neighing after his Neighbors Wife,</hi> whoſe Carkaſſes fell in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it is ſeen how juſt it was with God to deſtroy the Kings of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and to give to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> the <hi>Amorites,</hi> with their Country, becauſe they would not let them paſs thorow their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions into the promiſed Land of Reſt; therefore was <hi>Og</hi> King of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hon</hi> King of <hi>Heſhbon,</hi> deſtroyed with their People; and the Dominion of God came over them, and their Dominion and their Earth, which was taken from them, though they would not let the Righteous Nation paſſe thorow it, who were innocent and harmleſs, and would have paid them for all: And though <hi>Balak</hi> ſought Inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38351:22"/>and hired <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet God bleſſed them altogether, and rejected <hi>Balaam,</hi> who would have curſed for Promotion and Wages, whom God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the voice of the Aſſe, for he was earthly; and though the Lord bleſſed his People, yet <hi>Balaam</hi> taught <hi>Balak</hi> to caſt a ſtumbling-block before the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> namely, To Allure them with the Daughters of his Land, to commit Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with the People of the Land, for which the Anger of God was againſt His People; and by Faith <hi>Phineas</hi> ſtood on the Lord's part, and thruſt through <hi>Zimry</hi> and <hi>Cosby</hi> in their Fornication (though they were Princes Children) and turned away the Anger of God, and received the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of an <hi>Everlaſting Prieſthood:</hi> he was zealous for God, and took away the evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers from the Land.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it is ſeen how juſt it was with God to have <hi>Achan,</hi> deſtroyed, becauſe he diſobeyed the Commandment of the Lord, when by Faith the Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> fell down, and his mind run into the Earth; he coveted the two hundred ſheckles of Silver, and the Wedge of Gold, and the goodly Babyloniſh Garment; for which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38351:23"/>his Name became blotted out amongſt the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though he hid his deceit in the Earth.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it's ſeen, that it was juſt in <hi>Micaiah</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, that he ſpake the VVord of the Lord faithfully, though againſt the King and his Purpoſes, and the Four hundred Prophets, though he ſuffered for it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it's ſeen, how juſt it was in <hi>Elijah</hi> to declare the VVord of the Lord, though he was called <hi>a Troubler of Iſrael</hi> for it, and his Life fought to be made a prey upon; who was ſent after into many Nations, and amongſt many People, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he pleaſed not <hi>Jezebel</hi> and the King, and their Prieſts and Prophets: And it was juſt in <hi>Elijah</hi> when he witneſſed againſt the Deceit of the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> (who were great in the Kingdom, and fed at <hi>Jezebels</hi> Table Four hundred of them) to bring the People off them; whom he ſlew, when he had faithfully manifeſted their Deceit to the People, though <hi>Jezebel</hi> ſought his life for it. Now theſe were zealous for the Lord, and feared not the face of Man, nor to diſpleaſe the Rulers and Powers of the Earth, whom the falſe Prophets and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38351:23"/>ever ſought to pleaſe, and to be in favour withal.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Light</hi> it is ſeen, that it was juſt in <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet to teſtifie againſt <hi>Saul</hi> and his People, becauſe they fulfilled not the Word of the Lord, but let their minds run into the Earthly things, in reſerving the Fat and the Beſt, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſacrificing to God; but God would have <hi>Obedience,</hi> and <hi>not Sacrifice;</hi> and his Voice <hi>hearkened to,</hi> before the <hi>fat of Rams;</hi> So that <hi>Diſobedience</hi> was as <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,</hi> and <hi>Stubbornneſs</hi> as <hi>Inquity</hi> and <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory;</hi> And <hi>Saul</hi> ſaved <hi>Agag</hi> King of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek</hi> alive, whom <hi>Samuel</hi> ſlew: And the good Spirit of God departed from <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe he had diſobeyed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it is ſeen, that it was juſt in <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, to Reprove <hi>David,</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe he had tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it is ſeen, that it was juſt with the Lord to rend the Kingdom out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and of <hi>Solomon</hi> and his Son, becauſe <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> tranſgreſſed the Commandments of he Lord, and followed not the Lord fully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o do his Will, but took Wives of the Daughters of the Heathen, who drew his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart into Idolatry.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:38351:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:38351:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:38351:25"/>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> its ſeen that it was juſt and true Faithfulneſs in <hi>Mordecai</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> who feared and worſhiped the living God, that he would not bow down before proud <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> though he was the ſecond Ruler in the Kingdom, and the King had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded concerning him, that all men ſhould bow down before him and reverence him; this faithfull <hi>Mordicai</hi> would not bow, though it was the King's Commandment; he was ſubject to the Higher Power, the Power of Truth, in which he gave up his Life, and the Life of the whole Seed of the <hi>Jews</hi> in danger of being deſtroyed, rather than he would bow, contrary to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and God, unto whom he bowed, wrought deliverance for him, and for his People, and deſtroyed proud <hi>Haman</hi> &amp; his houſe, who was in the lower power, who was diſpleaſed that the Righteous bowed not before him. Here all may reade their figure, who are diſpleaſed that the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will not bow unto them now, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence them with bowing <hi>Hat</hi> and <hi>Knee,</hi> and giving flattering Titles of Honour to them, which for Conſcience ſake, and its Peace ſake, they cannot do; but bow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, worſhip God and honour God
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38351:25"/>and obey every Juſt and Righteous Law of man.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Light</hi> it is ſeen and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that the true Prophets of the Lord gave forth a juſt Teſtimony againſt the falſe Prophets, and falſe Teachers, and falſe Shepherds, and falſe Paſtors: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Lord's Prophet gave forth a faithful Teſtimony againſt the Prieſts, the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Watchmen, and ſaid they were all <hi>ignorant,</hi> they were all <hi>blind,</hi> they were all Shepherds <hi>that could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, ſleeping, lying down,</hi> and <hi>loving to ſlumber;</hi> yea, they were <hi>dumb dogs that could not bark; greedy dogs that never had enough, every one ſeeking for his gain from his quarter.</hi> Theſe had their minds run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to earthly things, and were juſtly teſtified againſt. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> juſtly teſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt. ſuch Prieſts, as <hi>bear Rule by their Means,</hi> and ſaid it was a filthy and horrible thing committed in the Land, <hi>That the Prieſts ſhould bear Rule by their Means, and the Prophets ſhould propheſie falſly, and the People love to have it ſo: but what will ye do in the end thereof,</hi> ſaith he? He likewiſe bore Teſtimony againſt ſuch Prieſts and Prophets who were <hi>light</hi> and <hi>treacherous,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:38351:26"/>who with <hi>Lyes</hi> and <hi>lightneſs</hi> made the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>light</hi> and <hi>vain;</hi> from whom <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Prophaneſs was gone into all Nations;</hi> They were to him <hi>Sodom,</hi> and as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Gomorrha;</hi> and ſaid <hi>the Lord was againſt them, who propheſied and uſed their tongues, and ſaid, The Lord ſaith, when as they had no other word, but what they ſtole from their Neighbours: Therefore the Lord ſaid, he was againſt them; they ran, and he never ſent them, and they ſhould not profit the People at all: who were telling their falſe dreams, and with their Lyes And Lightneſs made the People light and vain.</hi> This <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was put into the Dungeon for his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faithfully of the Truth of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both <hi>Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> And they that <hi>trembled</hi> at the Word of the Lord in his dayes, they were <hi>caſt out,</hi> unto whom he ſpake the Word of the Lord, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Hear ye the Word of the Lord, ye that tremble at the Word of the Lord; your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that hated yon, and caſt ye out, ſaid, Let the Lord be glorified: He ſhall ariſe your glory, and to their ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And through <hi>Faith Ezekiel</hi> teſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Shepherds and Teachers , as <hi>fed themſelves,</hi> and <hi>not the Flock; who fed with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38351:26"/>the Fat, and cloathed with the Wool, and made a Prey upon the People;</hi> who <hi>flattered the Ungodly, and put Cuſhions under their Armholes; ſpeaking Peace to the Wicked, and juſtifying the Ungodly for a thing of naught, while they put into their mouthes, and feed them with the fat;</hi> Theſe were in Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, one <hi>building a Wall,</hi> and another <hi>daub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with untempered Mortar who healed up the hurt of the Daughters of the People ſlightly, until they made the wound uncurable, and the ſouls that ſhould have lived became deſtroyed:</hi> This <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was a Sign and a Reproach amongſt them, and they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of him to be but an enditer of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Hoſea</hi> teſtified juſtly againſt the Prieſts who went in <hi>Cains</hi> way in envy; he ſaid, <hi>As a Company of Robbers wait for a man; ſo do the Company of Priests murder in the way by conſent, they commit Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it's ſeen, how juſt and faithful it was in <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednega,</hi> the Servants of the moſt High God, who would not bow at the King's Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; not bow to the Image, nor ſerve the god which <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the King
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38351:27"/>had ſet up, though it was aſſented unto by the People, and the Image dedicated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Rulers, the Captains, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and People of the Land and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, <hi>That all Nations, Kindreds, Tongues, and People, when they heard all the ſorts of Muſick ſhould fall down and worſhip; if not, to be caſt into the Fiery Furnace.</hi> But theſe faithful Servants of the Lord, though in Captivity, regarded not the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, but ſerved the living God, who delivered them by their <hi>Faith</hi> out of the Fiery Furnace, and out of the hands of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who would have forced them contrary to their Faith; who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was forced from his Kingdom, and driven from amongſt: Men, &amp;c. becauſe he was exalted in Pride againſt the Lord, and in the delight of earthly things; who ſaid, <hi>Is not this great Babel which I have built, by the might of my Power, for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of my Majeſty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that it was juſt in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> (who was come to pray in Faith and in the Spirit) that he would not be reſtrained from ſerving his God in the way as he was wont to do, though wicked Rulers and Princes betrayed the King, to make a Law
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38351:27"/>to enſnare him; which was called a firm Decree and unalterable, <hi>according to the Law of the Medes and Perſians:</hi> yet <hi>Daniel</hi> feared not, but ſerved his God according to his Conſcience, though it was againſt their Royal Law and firm Decree, which the King and Princes had made: and by his Faith was delivered out of the Den of Lions, and God ſtopped their mouthes. And theſe things are a faithful Teſtimony againſt all changable Prieſts, who crouch, and bow, and diſſemble with every Power of the Earth, who can but give them a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and will change their Faith, VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Religion, according to the Will of every Power that rules as Chief in the Nations; ſo that People cannot have any Certainty of truſting in them, nor in their Way, Faith, VVorſhip, nor Doctrine. And theſe things may ſerve as a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all in the <hi>True Faith,</hi> that they may continue in the exerciſe of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the pure Religion and Worſhip of God; believing, that that way which the Wicked may hope to deſtroy them for their Faith and Obedience, that way God is able to deliver and exalt them; as may be ſeen of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> the <hi>Three Children, Daniel,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:38351:28"/>and many others, who abode faithful to the death; and being throughly proved, were exalted; and their Enemies, who hoped to have deſtroyed them, were deſtroyed; and thus, through Faith and Comfort of the Scriptures, to have Hope and ſtrong Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Faith</hi> it's ſeen, that <hi>Micah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of the Lord, juſtly and righteouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt the Judges that judged for Reward; and againſt that grievous Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the <hi>Prieſts preaching for Hire,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets divining for Money,</hi> who ſpake Peace, and cryed, <hi>Peace, peace, while they put into their mouthes;</hi> but if they put not into their mouthes, then <hi>they prepareed war againſt them,</hi> Mica. 3. <hi>and yet they will lean upon the Lord, and ſay, No evil ſhall come upon them: But for their ſakes</hi> Sion <hi>ſhall be plowed as a field, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhall become an heap, and the Mountain of the Houſe of the Lord, as the high places of the Forreſt.</hi> Mark what deſolation here was becauſe of theſe things: though they ſaid. No evil ſhall come upon them, and cryed Peace, while they put into their mouthes, and gave them the hire, <hi>the Wages of Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> the Money for which they preach'd and divined.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:38351:28"/>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen how juſt it was in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> to declare the Word of the Lord faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, though againſt King <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and the Prieſts; and though he was but an Herdſman, and a gatherer of Sycamore fruits, yet called thereunto of God; againſt whom <hi>Amaziah</hi> Prieſt aroſe in Envy, to have expelled him out of their Coaſts; who complained againſt him to the King, and ſaid, <hi>the Land was not able to bear his words,</hi> and bid him <hi>flee Into the Land of</hi> Benjamin, <hi>and propheſie no more at</hi> Bethel, <hi>for it was the King's Chappel, and the Palace of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by Faith in the Light it is ſeen how juſt it was in <hi>Malachy</hi> to declare the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God, againſt the Prieſts who had violated the Law, and tranſgreſſed that which they ſhould have brought people to the obedience of, and to the fulfilling of, that if they did not <hi>Repent,</hi> God would <hi>curſe</hi> their <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> and ſpread the <hi>dung</hi> of their <hi>ſolemn Aſſemblies</hi> on their <hi>faces,</hi> and men ſhould carry them away; yea, <hi>I have curſed them already,</hi> faith the Lord. Now theſe Prieſts Lips <hi>ſhould have preſerved Knowledge,</hi> and the people <hi>ſhould have ſought the Law at their mouthes; for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38351:29"/>with</hi> Levi <hi>was Life and Peace for evermore, for he turned many from Iniquity to Righteouſneſs:</hi> but theſe <hi>violated the Law,</hi> and <hi>corrupted their doings,</hi> and <hi>tranſgreſſed that,</hi> Which they ſhould have brought peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>the obedience of;</hi> for which cauſe God <hi>rejected their doings,</hi> and <hi>curſed their Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,</hi> and they ſhould be <hi>no more</hi> Prieſts to Him: But unto us the true Prieſt is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <hi>CHRIST</hi> who hath written his Law in our hearts, and put it in our minds, ſo that we ſee the end of all the Prieſts, and cannot ſeek the Law at their mouths who divines it out for Money, and have no need to ſeek it of them; for we are come to the <hi>Everlaſting Law written in our hearts,</hi> the <hi>Covenant of God,</hi> wherein all know the Lord, and witneſs <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Life, at whoſe mouth we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Law, and He is the Preſerver of our Knowledge.</p>
            <p>By Faith it is ſeen, that it was juſt and righteous in Chriſt, to bid the <hi>Jews</hi> do as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſaid while they ſat in <hi>Moſes</hi> Seat, and read the Law, but not to follow after their works, nor their traditions which were vain, by which they made the Commandments of God of none effect,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38351:29"/>and this was ſpoken to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were under the Law (for under the Law, Chriſt was made of a Woman, to Redeem them that are under the Law) and the Law was to be fulfilled, which Chriſt is the <hi>End</hi> of, which he then witneſſed unto, that it was to be heard from their mouths; who when Chriſt was offered up, the <hi>End of the Law,</hi> the <hi>everlaſting Offering,</hi> the Apoſtles wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the contrary, that ſuch as had the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and denyed the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power, from ſuch turn away;</hi> for then they made but merchandize of Souls after Chriſt was come, and offered up, the <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Prieſt,</hi> who writes his Law in their, hearts, and puts it in their minds, that by it all may be taught of God, and ſo come off from the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> though they ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> Seat, whoſe Worſhip was vain, teaching for Doctrines the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men, drawing near with their mouths and lips, while their hearts were far from God.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that it was juſt and righteous in Chriſt to own the Tything of <hi>Mint, Annis</hi> and <hi>Rhue,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> (though he condemned the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> for omitting the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38351:30"/>weighty matters of the Law, Faith, Mercy, and Juſtice) for that was in the time alſo of the Law, and of the firſt <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and before the <hi>everlaſting Offering,</hi> was offered up, which is the <hi>end</hi> of the Law, &amp; the ſum of all Offerings; who <hi>blotted out the hand writing of Ordinances, and nailed them to his Croſs,</hi> which were againſt us; and raiſed up another Prieſthood, which was free, and ſent forth Miniſters to turn People to it, who had freely received, and were freely to give: and the Apoſtles never ſpake of Tythes to <hi>Gentiles,</hi> (nor Chriſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) but witneſſed the contrary; and that the firſt <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> which conſiſted in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Waſhings,</hi> and <hi>Meats,</hi> and <hi>Drinks</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the Tythes were payed)was changed, and the Law alſo, by which it was made, and by which the Tythes were payed under it, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. for the Law and the firſt <hi>Prieſthood</hi> made nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as appertaining to the Conſcience, but the bringing in of a better Hope did, by the which we draw nigh unto God, which is Chriſt, who is revealed in his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, an Anchor to their Souls, to keep them ſure and ſteadfaſt, and <hi>he is in us, the Hope of Glory; and he that hath this Hope
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38351:30"/>in him, purifies himſelf, even as he is pure:</hi> So that it's clearly ſeen, they that take Tythes now, are Antichriſtian; and they which pay them, deny the <hi>Everlaſting Offering,</hi> by <hi>which them that are ſanctified are perfected for ever;</hi> who is the <hi>End</hi> of the Law, and the changeable <hi>Prieſthood; who hath blotted out the hand writing of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, nailing them to his Croſs,</hi> and brought in the everlaſting Righteouſneſs, and the Spiritual Prieſthood, and the Hope which makes perfect, pertaining to the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>By Faith it is clearly ſeen, that God in his faithfulneſs, hath revealed his Son to finiſh Sin, and make an end of Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to cauſe the daily Offerings to ceaſe (for which ſake the Tythes were pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> of the firſt <hi>Prieſthood)</hi> and offered up himſelf upon the Croſs, to make peace between man and God, that all ſtrife might be ended; ſo he blotting out the Ordinances of the <hi>firſt Covenant,</hi> which were in old time, and ordains obedience for all His, that ſo as he makes peace with God, they may have peace with all men, and exerciſe a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence towards all, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38351:31"/>love their enemies, and reſiſt not evil, do good againſt evil, bleſs them that curſe, pray for them that diſpitefully uſe them; love their enemies, feed them when they are hungry, cloath them when they are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; <hi>if any one compels to go a mile, go with him twain; and if they ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn the other; and if they ſue thee at the Law, and take away thy coat, let them have thy cloak alſo; and do unto every one, as thou wouldſt be done unto; love the Lord thy God with all thy heart and ſoul, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf; this is the Royal Law and the Prophets,</hi> which the Goſpel, <hi>(which is the Power of God to Salvation)</hi> gives, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to fulfil, who doth believe in it, and obey it: Now he that comes to this, needs not ſwear at all, but in all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, let his <hi>yea, be yea,</hi> his <hi>nay, nay.</hi> Here's the end of Strife, the end of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the end of Fighting, the end of Wrangling and Suing at Law, and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and falſe Witneſs-bearing; the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpel, which is received by Faith in the Light, which gives to ſuffer all things, bear all things, forgive all things, committing every thing unto God, that judges righteouſly; and he that comes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38351:31"/>to this, will not ſtumble at Chriſt's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> nor at the Apoſtles Doctrine, who ſaith, <hi>My Brethren, above all things, ſwear not by any Oath, leſt ye fall into Condemnation, but let your yea, be yea, and your nay, nay, in all your Communications;</hi> and then it will be ſeen, that there is not a wiſe man amongſt them, that goes to Law with his Brother, and doth not chuſe rather to ſuffer wrong; and that ſuch have not the mind of Chriſt, who cannot ſuffer, though he ſuffered for all.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that Chriſt made it one of his greateſt Buſineſſes, and one of his chiefeſt Works, to witneſs againſt the <hi>Prieſts, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the moſt Woes againſt them than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any, for they laid heavy burdens upon the People, and devoured Widows Houſes, and under a pretence made long Prayers; theſe ſhould receive the greater damnation, and he cryed, Wo againſt them often, and called them Fools, and Blind, and Serpents, and Vipers, and asked them, <hi>how they could eſcape the Damnation of Hell, who were blind leaders of the blind?</hi> theſe were witneſſed againſt, for their <hi>ſtanding
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38351:32"/>praying in the Synagogues,</hi> and <hi>being called of men Maſters,</hi> and <hi>having the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies,</hi> and <hi>the greetings in the Markets,</hi> and <hi>walking in long Robes;</hi> and Chriſt commanded his Diſciples, not to be called of men Maſter, <hi>for one was their Maſter, ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Chriſt, and they were all Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;</hi> and he bid them beware of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> (to wit, their Doctrine) for it was Hypocriſie; they ſay and do not: here he brought them out from them, and did not bid them hear them any more, to do as they ſaid, for the Law was fulfilled, which Chriſt is the <hi>End</hi> of; and they were to Preach the Goſpel, and bring People off from the Temple, Synagogues and Aſſemblies of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to the Light and Power of God, to worſhip God in the Spirit, and in the Truth; and for Chriſt's witneſſing the Truth againſt theſe <hi>Prieſts, Phariſees, Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> they accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be mad, and to have a Devil, and to be a Blaſphemer; and ſo the <hi>Prieſts, Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Scribes,</hi> ſtirred up the Powers of the Earth againſt him, to put him to death, and to render him odious to the <hi>Rulers;</hi> and ſaid he was not <hi>Ceſars</hi> friend,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38351:32"/>and that he denyed to pay Tribute to <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi> and ſo through lyes and diſſimulation, ſtirred up both <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>People</hi> againſt the Lord of Life, the Lord of Glory, <hi>whom they took, with wicked hands, and ſlew, and hanged on a Tree, whom God raiſed up from the Dead,</hi> againſt whom the Envy of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> was not ſatisfied, but gave large moneys to raiſe lyes of him after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, which were believed among the <hi>Jews</hi> unto this day.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, how juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous the Judgement of Chriſt was againſt them, who were once bidden to the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Supper</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> (who when all things on the Kings part were provided for them, began to make excuſes, one by one; the one hanging in the <hi>Farm,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Yoak,</hi> of <hi>Oxen,</hi> and the other taking a <hi>Wife, and could not come</hi>) to reject them all; &amp; if the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were firſt bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, could not taſte of his <hi>Supper,</hi> becauſe of theſe things: wherewith can the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> be found worthy, but by coming out of them, into the obedience of the Truth? and to come out of the Earth, out of the High-wayes, and Hedges, and Streets, where there hath been lameneſs, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38351:33"/>blindneſs, and hardneſs of heart, which the <hi>Gentile,</hi> if he comes in, hath not the <hi>VVedding garment,</hi> and to him it will be ſaid, <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou hither, not having a VVedding garment? and he ſhall be taken, and caſt into utter darkneſs, where there ſhall be weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> Therefore all are to look about them, and mind to obey that which is of God, that you may have the <hi>VVed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing garment,</hi> the cloathing of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which, whoſoever feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs in all Nations, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſhall be accepted; but anguiſh, pain and tribulation, to the Soul of every one that doth Evil, <hi>to the Jew firſt, and likewiſe to the Gentile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Faith it is ſeen, how juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous it was for the Apoſtles and Servants of Chriſt to meet togetter, in the Faith, and in the Fear of the Lord, to wait toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Promiſe of the Father; which ſaid Chriſt, <hi>ye have heard of me, and ye ſhall receive Power from on High, when the Holy Ghoſt is come upon you; and ye ſhall be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes unto me, both at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and in</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea; and they through waiting received the Promiſe, the Power from on High, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38351:33"/>the Holy Ghoſt came upon them; and through the Power of the Higheſt, were moved to go into the Nations, and unto the People which dwelt upon the Earth, Preaching the Goſpel freely, as they had received freely, labouring in the Power of the Higheſt, to turn People from the Darkneſs and Error of their Lives, unto the Light, and to the Knowledge of the Light of the Glorious Goſpel, which ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their hearts, to give them the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, and Preached the Word of Faith in their hearts, and in their mouths; and <hi>that they had a more ſure Word of Propheſie, unto which they did well to take heed, as unto a Light that ſhined in a dark place, until the day dawned, and the day Star aroſe in their hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Faith it is ſeen, how juſt it was in the Apoſtles, to go forth, Preaching the Goſpel to all Nations, though commanded by the <hi>Rulers, to ſpeak no more in that Name, yet they ſpoke the more boldly;</hi> going into Markets, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, and Aſſemblies of the People, though oppoſed by <hi>Prieſts,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rulers,</hi> &amp; <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> &amp; caſt into priſons, &amp; under ſore Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and Bonds, and many Tryals, yet
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38351:34"/>they went on boldly, not regarding the Commandment of men, <hi>but obeyed God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, how juſt it was in them, to witneſs againſt falſe Worſhips, falſe Teachers, falſe Apoſtles, falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, falſe Miniſters, laying them open by their Fruits, as Chriſt had ſaid, when he propheſied, that <hi>many falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets ſhould come, and ſhould deceive many; by their fruits ye ſhall know them;</hi> and by their fruits the Apoſtles laid them open, who were falſe Miniſters, Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Satan, Miniſters of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, transforming themſelves into the likeneſs of the Miniſters of Chriſt, who went in <hi>Cain's</hi> way, envying, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Juſt, and in <hi>Balaam's</hi> way, <hi>for Wages of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> and Promotion, and Gifts, and Rewards; who minded earthly things, whoſe God was their Belly, and their glory in their ſhame, <hi>whoſe end was to be deſtroyed; who with good words, and fair ſpeeches, deceived the hearts of the ſimple, and through covetouſneſs made merchandiſe of Souls, bringing in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and preach for Money and Price;</hi> when as the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38351:34"/>Lord ſaid, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give,</hi> the Work-man is worthy of his meat; theſe had eyes full of Adultery, and could not ceaſe from ſinning, beguiling unſtable Souls, whoſe hearts are exerciſed with covetous Practices, curſed Children, which have forſaken the right Way, and are gone aſtray, after the error of <hi>Balaam;</hi> who loved the Wages of unrighteouſneſs; but the dumb Aſs ſpeaking with man's Voice, rebuked ſuch madneſs in him, who was greedying after earthly things. And the Apoſtles witneſſed againſt ſuch Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that ſpoke things which they ought not, for filthy lucre ſake, who were proud men, who were <hi>covetous men, heady, high-minded, treacherous, diſobedient to Parents, unthankful, unholy, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, truce-breakers, incontinent, fierce,</hi> diſpiſers of thoſe that are good, <hi>lovers of Pleaſures more than lovers of God, having a Form of Godlineſs, but denying the Life and Power thereof; from ſuch turn away: for of this ſort are they which creep into Houſes, leading ſilly Women captive, laden with ſin, and led away with divers luſts, ever learning, but never able to come to the Knowledge of the Truth; and as</hi> Jannes <hi>and</hi> Jambres <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:38351:35"/>Moſes, <hi>ſo do theſe withſtand the Truth; men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the Faith, being Evil men, and Seducers, waxing worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived;</hi> but they ſhall proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, their folly ſhall be manifeſt to all men. And <hi>Jude</hi> witneſſeth againſt ſuch as were ungodly men, <hi>turning the Grace of our Lord Jeſus into laſciviouſneſs,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the only Lord and Saviour; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them Wells without water, ſpots in their Feaſts, feeding without Fear, Clouds carried about with Wind, filthy Dreamers, that defile the Fleſh; who went in <hi>Cain</hi>'s way, and <hi>Balaam</hi>'s way, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, being ſeparated, ſenſual, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not the Spirit: And the Apoſtle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt them, who were given to Wine, and that were Strikers &amp; Lovers of Money, &amp; of filthy Lucre (&amp; bid the Saints take heed of ſuch that were deſirous of filthy Lucre) that were ſelf-willed, who deſpiſed Dominion, and ſpoke evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, natural bruit Beaſts, made to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and deſtroyed; (as all the Prieſts of the World, deſpiſe that any can come into that Dignity or Dominion, as to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38351:35"/>Sin, and to be throughly cleanſed in this Life, and perfected.)</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that all theſe that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified againſt ſuch as lived in theſe Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, before mentioned, were juſt and faithful unto God; and it's likewiſe ſeen to be juſt and faithfulneſs in us, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt all ſuch that live in ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices that they were in, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and all the Saints teſtified againſt, though the world could not bear it then, to have their Teachers and Prophets declared againſt, neither can they now; yet it's juſt with God, and in faithfulneſs to the Lord, to declare againſt them, who are manifeſt by their Fruits, to be in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets; <hi>by their Fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for an evil Tree cannot bring forth good Fruit, nor a good Tree cannot bring forth evil Fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that it was juſt with God to ſmite <hi>Herod</hi> the King (who had ſtretched forth his hand to vex certain of the Church, and perſecuted the Saints) when he had made an Oration before the People, who gave a ſhout, and ſaid it was the Voice of a God, and not of a man, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38351:36"/>that the worms ſhould eat him, becauſe he gave not the Glory to God.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's ſeen, that it was great faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and obedience unto the Lord in the Apoſtles, that they gave up themſelves to do the Work of God, and laboured in the Truth, to turn both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> to Chriſt, the true Light, which enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every one that cometh into the World; and to the Grace which hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men, which taught the Saints that denying ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, they might live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent World, and come to know the ſaving of their Souls, by the Grace through Faith; and when the People did once believe, they came to receive Grace for Grace, and had Faith revealed in them, from Faith to Faith, which gave them Victory over the whole World, and over the Tranſgreſſion of it, to be cleanſed from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting Holineſs in the Fear of God; and unto ſuch the Apoſtles wrote Epiſtles, exhorting them to continue in the Faith, and to perſevere in the Hope, Watching and being Sober, having the loynes of their minds girt about with the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38351:36"/>Truth; unto theſe Salvation was come nearer than when they firſt Believed; therefore they were to awake from ſleep, and riſe, from dead Works, and to put off the deeds of the Night; for the Darkneſs was paſt, and the true Light ſhined, and they were to put on the whole Armour of God, to Arm themſelves with the Armour of Light, that they might withſtand the evil Day, and might be able to quench the fiery Darts of the Devil; that they might offer their Bodies unto God, a Living, Holy Sacrifice, acceptable unto God, which was but their reaſonable Service; not faſhioning themſelves according to the Faſhions of the World, but to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in their Mindes, to prove what is that good and acceptable, and perfed Will of God: And they were not to adorn themſelves with Gold, or Silver, or Pearls or Plaiting of Hair, nor coſtly Array, but with modeſt Apparel, to adorn the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel of Chriſt; Let not your adorning be with the putting on of Apparel, nor wearing of Gold, or Pearls, ar broidered Hair, but let it be in the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den man of the Heart, with a meek and quiet Spirit, which with the Lord is of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38351:37"/>great price; and their words were to be few, and ſeaſoned with ſalt, that they might adminiſter Grace to the Hearers; that all things might be done in Order, and decently, for the ſetting forth the Glory of God, and the Praiſe of his Grace, by which they were called to be Saints.</p>
            <p>By Faith it's likewiſe ſeen, that after the Apoſtles had once turned the People to the true Light, and to know God ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in their Hearts, to cauſe the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, to give them the Light of the Knowledge of his Glory, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, in which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Anointing, which gave them an underſtanding to know all things, ſo that they needed no man to teach them; then they committed them to the Word of his Grace, which was able to keep them from falling, and left them to aſſemble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together in the Spirit, to worſhip God in the Spirit, and in the Truth, and not to forſake the aſſembling themſelves together <hi>(as the manner of ſome was)</hi> but to wait for the Promiſes, and perſevere in the Hope unto the end, waiting for the appearing of the great God and his Chriſt; then they left them, committing them to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38351:37"/>the Grace which was able to keep them from falling, and to the Spirit of Jeſus, which was able to build them up, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o keep them from the world unſpotted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to hate even the garment ſpotted with the Fleſh, and to preſent them Holy unto God, without ſpot or blemiſh, or any ſuch like thing; which brought them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> one another, and to have Union one w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h another, and not with the world (for a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever and an Infidel cannot concord) then I ſay they left them, and did not continue with them, as the manner of Hirelings ever was, to ſtay as long as they lived, for great ſums of Money, with one People (except they could get a greater <hi>Benefice</hi> with another) whoſe day is as the cutting off Life from the Earth, and going down to the Grave; but the Apoſtles day, was to do the joyful Work of God, and to call many into the Light, the way of <hi>everlaſting Reſt,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Joy;</hi> who, when they had turned one People to the Light, left them, and wrote to them from another People, unto whom they were gone to turn them to the ſame Truth, and out of other Lands: So they ſaluted the Saints and their Aſſemblies (which they had ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered)
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38351:38"/>with the ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations of Peace and Love, exhorting all to preſs forward to the Mark of the price of the High Calling in Chriſt Jeſus; namely, to the full at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the fulneſs of an Holy and perfect Life, that they might all be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented perfect in Chriſt, and ſanctified throughout, in Soul, Body and Spirit, and being partakers of the Divine Nature, and eſcaping the Corruption which is in the world, through luſt, and being partakers of the Faith, <hi>they might give all diligence, to make their Calling and Election ſure; adding unto Faith, Vertue, and unto Vertue, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to Knowledge, Temperance, and to Temperance, Patience, and to Patience, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and to Godlineſs, brotherly Love, and to brotherly Love, Charity,</hi> (which is the band that keepeth perfect) <hi>for if theſe things be in you and abound, they make you, that you ſhall neither be barren, nor unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the Knowledge of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt; but he that lacketh theſe things, is blind, and cannot ſee afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old ſins: Wherefore the rather Brethren, give all diligence, to make your Calling and Election ſure; for if ye do theſe things, ye ſhall never
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38351:38"/>fall; and ſo an entrance ſhall be miniſtred unto you abundantly, into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I have given forth, from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and uprightneſs of my Heart, as moved of the Lord, which I ſend abroad, as a Teſtimony of the true Work of the true Faith, and of its Effect; it being a few of thoſe excellent Truths, which through Faith in the Light, is given me to ſee, and to believe, and to witneſs forth the true Teſtimony of the Saints, which juſtly and truly they through Faith witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed forth, to the Glory of God; and it is to be Printed and ſent abroad unto all People, but moſt eſpecially to all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> and the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and the Iſlands thereunto belonging; which if in this I ſhould finiſh my Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, of Writing or Declaring the Truth of God, yet this ſhall ſtand unto Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to come, and to this preſent Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as a Teſtimony of the Truth, learned by Faith, which ſhall be witneſſed by the Light in every one's Conſcience, to be true; which whoſoever believes in the true Light, which enlightens every one,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38351:39"/>
               <hi>ſhall ſee greater things than theſe,</hi> and that by Faith it's poſſible to know all things, and to know God, whom to know, is Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Virginia,</hi> by a Lover of the Truth, and a Believer in the true Light.</dateline>
               <signed>G. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>Concerning Waiting upon the Lord, in ſtilneſs, and in ſilence.</head>
            <p>VVHen <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in diſtreſs, they were commanded to hold their peace, <hi>and ſtand still, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord,</hi> and the Lord ſhould fight for them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13, 14. and when they ſtood ſtill, then the Lord revealed his Arm, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved &amp; delivered them: But when they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted the Lord, and looked to <hi>Egypt</hi> for help, the Lord ſaid, <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhould help in vain, &amp; to no purpoſe; <hi>Therfore have I cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning this, their ſtrength is to ſit ſtill:</hi> Mark, to <hi>ſit ſtill</hi> was their ſtrength; <hi>and in returning and reſt ſhall ye be ſaved, in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:38351:39"/>quietneſs and in confidence ſhall be your ſtrength, Iſa.</hi> 30.7, 15. But they would not, but ſaid no, <hi>We will flee upon the ſwift.</hi> Mark, here's a way of their own finding; <hi>therefore the ſwift ſhould purſue them, and one thouſand ſhould flee at the rebuke of one, and at the rebuke of five ſhall ye flee, till ye be left as a Beacon on the top of a Mountain, and as an Enſign on a Hill.</hi> Now mark, what became of them, who would not <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> who would not <hi>Wait;</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> being affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and his Friends came to viſit him, <hi>they ſate ſilent, waiting ſeven dayes, Job</hi> 2.13. And all may ſee it was the way of the Saints to be in <hi>ſtilneſs,</hi> and in <hi>ſilence,</hi> and in <hi>waiting; for bleſſed are all they that wait upon the Lord, Iſa.</hi> 30.18. And <hi>David</hi> ſayes, <hi>I wait for the Lord, my ſoul doth wait, and in his VVord do I hope; my ſoul waiteth for the Lord, more than they that watch for the morning;</hi> I ſay, <hi>more than they that watch for the morning, Pſa.</hi> 130.5, 6. and <hi>rest in the Lord, wait patiently for him, Pſa.</hi> 37.7. <hi>And the Youths ſhall faint and be weary, and the Young-men ſhall utterly fall; but they that wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength; they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, and they ſhall walk
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38351:40"/>and not faint Iſa.</hi> 40.30, 31. <hi>And the ſtrong Lyon ſhall ſuffer want, and the young Lyon ſhall ſuffer hunger; but he that waiteth upon the Lord ſhall not want any good thing. I will ſtand upon my watch, and ſet me on the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and will watch to ſee, what the Lord will ſay unto me</hi> (or ſpeak in me) <hi>and what I ſhall anſwer when I am reproved; and let all fleſh keep ſilent before the Lord,</hi> Hab. 2. <hi>for every man's own words ſhal be his burden,</hi> Jer. 23. <hi>Keep ſilent before me, O Iſlands, and let the People renew their ſtrength; for the Iſles ſhall wait for his Law,</hi> Iſa. 42.4. <hi>Yea, in the way of thy Judgements, O Lord, have we waited for Thee, the deſire of our ſoul is to thy Name, and to the remembrance of Thee; with my ſoul have I deſired Thee, In the night: yea, with my ſpirit within me will I ſeek Thee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for when thy Judgements are in the Earth, the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteouſneſs, Iſa.</hi> 26.8, 9. Note this well, how they were to <hi>wait,</hi> and how they <hi>waited,</hi> and ſought the Lord: <hi>Hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me my People, and give ear unto me, O my Nation, for a Law ſhall proceed from me, and I will make my Judgement to reſt for a Light of the People; my Righteouſneſs is near, my Salvation Is gone forth, and mine Arms ſhall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38351:40"/>judge the People; the Iſles ſhall wait upon me, and on mine Arm ſhall they truſt, Iſa.</hi> 51.4, 5. <hi>For ſince the beginning of the World, men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye ſeen, O God, beſides thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him, Iſa.</hi> 64.4. <hi>The Lord is good unto them that wait for him, to the ſoul that ſeeketh him: It is good that a man ſhould both hope, and quietly wait for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lord; it is good for a man, that he bear the yoak in his youth; he ſitteth alone, and keepeth ſilence, becauſe he hath borne it upon him; he putteth his mouth in the duſt, if ſo be there may be hope,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25, &amp;c. <hi>And they ſhall every man ſit under his own Vine, und under his own Figge-tree, and none ſhall make them afraid, Mica.</hi> 4. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore turn thou to thy God, keep Mercy and Judgement, and wait on thy God continually, Hoſ.</hi> 12.6. Hence all may ſee the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Saints, in the dayes of the Prophets; and how all are commanded to <hi>wait</hi> and hope in the Lord, and to be quiet and ſtill, hoping on the God of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Whereſoever two or three are met together in my Name, there am
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38351:41"/>I in the midſt of them, Mat.</hi> 18.20. <hi>And can ye not watch one hour? and what I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all, Watch; for bleſſed ſhall he be that ſhall be found ſo doing, when the Son of man cometh, Mark</hi> 13. and the five fooliſh <hi>Virgins,</hi> who waited not, nor watcht to have their <hi>Lamps</hi> kept burning, but gadded abroad, were ſhut out of the <hi>Kingdom, Mat.</hi> 25. and <hi>Simeon,</hi> a juſt man, <hi>waited</hi> for the conſolation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to him it was revealed, that he ſhould not ſee death, until he had ſeen the Lord's Chriſt; and when he ſaw the Salvation of God, the Light to enlighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and Glory of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> deſired <hi>to depart in Peace, Luk.</hi> 2. And when Chriſt was ready to aſcend to the Father, he commanded his Diſciples not to depart from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> until they had received the Promiſe of the Father, <hi>which</hi> ſaid he, <hi>ye have heard of me; and ye ſhall receive Power from on High, when the Holy Ghoſt is come upon you, and ye ſhall be Witneſſes unto me.</hi> Mark, when they had received the Power from on High, through <hi>waiting,</hi> then they ſhould be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes unto Him, <hi>both at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and in</hi> Judea, <hi>Act.</hi> I. And the Apoſtle exhorted the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to watch, and ſtand faſt in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38351:41"/>the Faith; <hi>Quit you like men, be ſtrong,</hi> I <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13. And he told the Saints, that they were not of Darkneſs, nor Children of the Night, but Children of the Light, and of the Day; <hi>therefore let us not ſleep,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as others do, but let us watch and be ſober; for they that ſleep, ſleep in the Night, and they that be drunken, are drunken in the Night; but let us, who are of the Day, be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, putting on the Breaſt-plate of Faith and Love, and for an Helmet, the Hope of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> I <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. And he exhorted <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> to watch in all things, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. and they which ſhould be found not watching, the Lord would come upon them, <hi>as a Thief in the Night, Rev.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Behold, I come as a Thief: bleſſed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his garments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame, Rev.</hi> 16.15. So now all may ſee, that there muſt be a <hi>waiting,</hi> and there muſt be a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ye may ſtand in the Evil Day, that you may reſiſt the Enemy of your Souls; therefore put on the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God, that you may withſtand the Evil; put on the Armour of Light, that you may be able to quench the fiery Darts of the Devil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. So now, all that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38351:42"/>come to know the Covenant of God, and to walk in obedience to his Law, that he writes in the heart, and puts in the mind; that every man need not ſay to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and Brother, <hi>Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know him, Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. Theſe I ſay, muſt come to the <hi>waiting,</hi> and watching, in the Light, which Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Devil and his fiery Darts, that you may come to be eſtabliſhed in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; for all the People of God ſhall be taught of God, and eſtabliſhed in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and far from Oppreſſion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.14, 15. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.45. Now who comes to know this Promiſe fulfilled, muſt come to know the <hi>waiting</hi> in the Light, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God, that ye may know an <hi>VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTION</hi> from the <hi>Holy One,</hi> by which ye may know all things, as the Saints did, I <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.20, 27. who were anointed in their Souls, by the Eternal Spirit, and the Anointing which they had received of <hi>God</hi> abode in them, which taught them all things; ſo that they needed not that any man ſhould teach them, but as the ſame Anointing taught them all things which were true, and of it is no lye; and as it taught them, they were to abide in Him.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:38351:42"/>
            <p>And now all that come to wait and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Knowledge of theſe things, need not any to teach them, <hi>but all ſhall be taught of God,</hi> and eſtabliſhed in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; ſo that they will not need any man to teach them.</p>
            <closer>Glory in the Higheſt.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <head>A Viſitation to the Called of God, every where.</head>
            <p>FRiends, I conſider the former dayes, when God firſt made known unto us his Son, to be a Light unto us, to enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten us, and every one that cometh into the World; which manifeſted unto us, all that ever we had done, and judged Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in us, in all its appearances; then we believed in it, and had <hi>Grace for Grace</hi> manifeſted, and Faith revealed, from <hi>Faith</hi> to <hi>Faith;</hi> ſo that the Light being believed in (in which the Hope of Eternal Life came to be ſeen and laid hold on) then was the Love ſtrong, which ran forth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards die Lord, and his Truth; and the breakings into true Tenderneſs, and into
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38351:43"/>the true Fear and Humility, and the real-heartedneſs for God came to be ſeen and felt, in which the bringing out of the World came to be ſeen, and the true Zeal for God; ſo that through obedience in the Faith to the Light, nothing was too dear to be forſaken, and parted withal; and a true enquiring into the ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there was to ſee, how it was between God and every Soul; and then in the Light, both Words and Actions came to be weighed, and an enquiring into the Worlds wayes, of Deceit and Words, to deny them, their Wayes and Words, and their corrupt Language. Oh! the heart-breakings that were in that day, and the revealings of Secrets, and the manifeſting God's Power; which begat into the true Croſs, and truly to croſs that mind and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which had tranſgreſſed, both in thought, word, and deed: So that the Lord aroſe in the Glory of his Majeſty, to ſhake terribly the Earth, and to abaſe the fleſh, and lay low the glory of man, as thouſands can witneſs; then earthly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, and Riches, and Preferments, came to be lightly eſteemed on, and caſt off; yea, all of them that did let or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38351:43"/>Then ſtrong was the Love of God, and mightily did his Power work, to bring out of all things which were contrary to the Lord, and to the rooting out every Plant, which the Heavenly Father had not planted. In this day, Friends, could ye wrong any? Was not every one's care to be found innocent, juſt, upright, and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, having your Conſciences exerciſed, pure, and void of offence, towards God and man? could ye then at all bow to the World, or to their Wayes, Worſhips, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Words, or Performances? could ye then partake with them, almoſt in any thing at all? was not this a precious day, and a day of Love? could ye not endure all thing in this day, and ſuffer all things, and bear all things? and was any thing too hard then to do or perform? did not your Souls even hate all the corrupt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the Sons and Daughters of men, in that day when the Zeal and Power of God broke forth? could any temptation of the wicked enſnare you? was not the Light preſent to judge and condemn eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry temptation, and through its Judgement to deliver you? Oh! the Beauty and the Glory of that day, when God ſhook the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38351:44"/>Heavens, and made the Earth to tremble, and brake ſtony hearts at his pleaſure, and overturned <hi>Babylon,</hi> as a thing of naught, and brought forth many Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters unto Glory; my heart is broken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, when I call to mind this day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God did valiantly, and wrought excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things: How were the hearts of many drawn after him? how did their Love flow forth? how were they gathered by God? how quick was the Lord to execute Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice, and to ſet up his Truth in the hearts, and to confound the wiſdom of all fleſh? He gathered thouſands in his Love to deny themſelves, and all their own Wiſdom and Knowledge, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as little Children; yea, as new Born Babes, to wait at the breaſts of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they might learn both what to do, and what to ſpeak; yea, in that day the Lord made of a little one a thouſand, and of a ſmall People a ſtrong Nation; ſo that nothing was too hard for him to do: When I ſaw it I was glad, and truſted in the Lord, who in that day fitted many to his Service, and for his Honour and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for then he was ſwift in executing Judgement upon the World, and in caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38351:44"/>out the Prince of this World; ſo that he ſetled many to wait upon him, and it was their delight to do his Will, for his Love conſtrained them; and he was with them in their Aſſemblies, and bleſſed them when they <hi>waited</hi> in <hi>ſtilneſs</hi> and <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi> then were their tears as a <hi>Fountain,</hi> and the dropping down of their eye-lids, <hi>as the dew of Heaven.</hi> Oh! how precious it is to dwell in the tender Love of the Lord, then they thought the time long, until they were come together; and they <hi>waited</hi> in <hi>ſilence,</hi> until the Heavens dropped down <hi>dew,</hi> and their <hi>Conſolation</hi> came from God; ſo that none <hi>waited</hi> in vain, who <hi>waited</hi> in the Lord; for the Mountains melted at his preſence, the Earth trembled, the Rocks were rent, and the Clouds van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed away, and the Glory of the Lord filled his Sanctuary, and he threw out the <hi>Buyers</hi> and <hi>Sellers</hi> out of his <hi>Temple,</hi> and the <hi>Money-changers,</hi> and overthrew their <hi>Seat;</hi> then cloathed he himſelf with Zeal, as with a Cloak, for the day of Vengeance was in his heart, and he ſent forth his Sons and Daughters with his Word, to run to and fro in the Earth, and gave them hearts, as <hi>the heart of a Lion, and ſtrength that turned
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38351:45"/>away from none;</hi> ſo that his day of Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance became proclaimed; for he ordained ſtrength in the mouths of <hi>Babes and Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> when he ſhut out the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> of the World: This was the day in which God opened the door of Confuſion, unto the Diviners of the Earth, and turned the Prophets and their Seers into mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſo that to them, all is become as the Viſion of the night; night is upon them, they cannot divine; fearfulneſs ſurprizes them, they have changed their work, and bleſſe themſelves in their Railings, and Envyings, and Blaſphemies againſt the choſen Heir, becauſe he is too ſtrong for them, and holds them bound in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit, where they have now neither beginning nor end, nor place to reſt, but have ſtirred up the ſmoak thereof to darken the Earth, and to corrupt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of it, that they may lift up their laſt weapon for them, and exerciſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and laſt Power, and Strength, and Victory for them; but alas! hath not the Lord our God, in whom we believe, and upon whom we wait and ſerve, day and night, broken their ſtrength often times, as it were but a burnt thread or Flax,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38351:45"/>which had been burned in the fire? hath he not rebuked the Powers of the Earth, becauſe of them, and overturned the mighty from their Seats, becauſe of their hearkening to their deceits, who have been as Catter-pillers of the Earth, deſtroying both good and bad, as far as they can reach? and hath not the Lord taken us out of their Priſons, and Bonds, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of murder, from time to time? what valiant thing hath not the Lord done for his Choſen, who believe in his Light, that according as he hath purpoſed, they may be ordered to bear the Image of his Son? hath he ſuffered any thing to be done, but that which makes for his own purpoſe? have not ſufferings confirmed and builded up many in the Faith, when as they have been exerciſed in them for a moment, as it were to prove them for good? and then hath he not delivered out of them, in Glory and great Dominion? and hath he not done a double ſervice this way, in ſuffering theſe things? have not thouſands been convinced thereby, and way made in many places and Towns, for the Truth to enter? hath he not manifeſted the deceit of this Generation of Prieſts
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38351:46"/>there-through, ſo that thouſands never thought in their hearts to have ſeen, nor that it had been in their hearts to have done ſo as they have done? and if they have drank of our blood, is it not that they may be overcome thereby, and by Faith and Patience? and have not they, and their Rulers perſecuted and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, to make us grow, and encreaſe, and be ſtrong, and eſtabliſhed, and multilied? hath not the Lord done valiantly through all theſe things? (though the Evil-doers weaken their ſelves, and deſtroy their own Souls daily thereby) yea, and valiant things will he yet do, until he hath fully compleated his purpoſe; for his Son ſhall Reign, and he ſhall certainly overturn all that oppoſe his Work; and every one that riſeth againſt him in it, it will be his own breaking in pieces; for the Lord is making a ſhort work, who will finiſh it in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and wil make all ſerve for his own purpoſe, either to ſave, or to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now ſeeing theſe things are ſo, and that all hath wrought for good, who ſhould not Fear? who ſhould not Love the Lord? who ſhould not hold faſt the beginning of their Conſidence unto the end, and their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38351:46"/>Faith which God gave unto them, when they firſt received the Light, which brought into the Work, and into the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Zeal for God, and into the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to be bowed in all things unto the Lord, and into the Silence, and into the Meetings, and Fellowſhip, and Waiting upon the Lord? Now when I conſider the infinite Love, and unſearchable Wiſdom of God in all things that he ſuffereth and doth, and how he turns all to his own end, my heart is even broken within me, and my bowels yearn after many, that many might come to believe in the Light, where they might ſee the unſpeakable Love and Wiſdom of God; and for many doth my ſoul travel, and ſeeks unto God with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſires, and fervent Love, which I have ſeen the Lord anſwering; but for many, who were once partakers in the Works that God began to work, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the day, and of the love and mercies which God began to beſtow; I could even bewail my ſelf, and take up a lamentation over them, and could pour down with mine eyes as a flood, and make my place ſolitary, becauſe of the lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of many ſouls, and the faintneſs of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38351:47"/>many hearts: How ſoon was the Lilly torn among the Daughters? how faded their Beauty away? and how was the ſinging of Birds amongſt them, ſo ſoon ſilenced? how came their Spring to be turned into Winter, and their Sun to ſet in the Eaſt? their Morning turned into darkneſs, their Sun was drawn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with darkneſs in the Eaſt, their Morning came not forth in their haſte; they ſtumbled, and while they were aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring they fell; their ſtrength ſtood not in the Virgin, therefore they fell, and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with the earthly, and that are them out; their Beauty became as a fading flower, becauſe they truſted not in God their Saviour, but forſook their firſt Love: The young men liked the Lord well, while they ſtood in his Innocency; but when the Earth aroſe, the eye looked not towards God. Oh! that that liberty had been ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and the ſanctification come into, then ſhould the Scepter have been eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and the Croſs have been kept down [that earing worm] and the deſire of the heart ſhould have ſtood in the Lord, who therein fulfilleth every deſire in his own appointed time, but haſtineſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38351:47"/>many. Oh the ſorrow of the Juſt, and the burdens which have come upon the upright, becauſe many have ſtumbled by the way, and pierced their own ſouls through, and turned the day of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to blackneſs to themſelves, whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Dominion is fallen in the Earth, and their ſtrength fallen by the way, who have weakened their own hands, and the Praiſe of the Work is given to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; but all this hath the Lord ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the eſtabliſhing his Choſen, and the building up his Elect, on whom his Spirit reſteth; ſo that things which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſtrange, the Lord turns them all to good, and maketh the evil to be as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that all may fear and be humble before him; and aſſuredly every one that hath taſted of the day, and hath not kept the Faith, nor walked unſpotted of the World, even hating the Garment ſpotted with the fleſh; they ſhall bear their own burdens, and the Truth is clear, and in it there is no inſufficiency, though ſome have forſaken their firſt Faith, and not kept to their firſt Love: But unto all ye precious Sons and Daughters, who have kept the Faith, and grown up ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:38351:48"/>of your firſt Love, in the abundance of the Power and Vertue of the Lord, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you doth the Salutation of my Love reach, and my Life ſprings forth, and ſtreams towards you, which nothing can hinder; for the Lord hath enlarged me in his Life and Power, ſo that my Soul flows forth, in the abundance of his Love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, to be felt and known of all the Faithful; for my life and ſtrength is given up for the Service of the Lord, and cannot be ſeparated from you, but muſt be known and felt; though to the outward ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Work of the Lord, yet in that which is alwayes near, wherein the Lord doth bleſs his Work, and proſper his Truth, wherein I lye down in the Faith and Love, giving up, and being given up in all things to the Work of the Lord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the earneſt deſire of my Soul, that we may all give up, with one conſent, in Faith and Love, to do the Will of the Lord, and not to ſtagger or be diſmayed at any thing, whatſoever ſhall come to paſs in the Earth, we may witneſs forth the Truth boldly, as we have already done, bearing all things, ſuffering all things, and enduring all things joyfully; for the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38351:48"/>Lord is merciful, and will ſuffer nothing to come upon any, but what will make for good, and to fit them unto glory, as all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide-faithful unto him; and in this I bid you all farewel, for my Love is with you, and my life reaches you, in the Salutation of Peace and Love, having you often in my Remembrance.</p>
            <p>And all ye who have taſted of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of the Work of the Lord, unto whom the Light in ſome meaſure hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, yet the coming forward hath been but ſlowly; unto you, I ſay let the Light ſearch, that you may ſee wherein your hinderance ſtands, and what it is that lets; for in the true Light, and Love, and Faith of it, there is no inſufficiency, no weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no ſtraitneſs, for the ſtraitneſs is in your ſelves, and of your ſelves, and ſtands in that which opens the eye, to look into the pleaſure of the delights of the Sons and Daughters of men, and of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things; which when they are looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſomething likes them, takes delight, and ſeeks to advantage it ſelf in them, and this is the ſnare and hinderance, which being given place unto, then the Juſt ſuffers; and ſo that which ſhould ſtrengthen
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38351:49"/>and build up in the Power that miniſters Judgment; yea, &amp; through Judgment muſt the Juſt be raiſed: therefore ariſe, be awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, ſhake your ſelves, of the Encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, and of the Earth, that the Virgin-Seed may be raiſed, which will keep your minds ſtaid on God, and bring ye into the one Life, where ye may feel true ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the enjoyment of the Lord, and the Temptations ye may be redeemed out of, and may ſee the Ground from whence they do ariſe, namely, the mind &amp; nature which hath not God to be its full delight, but would delight it ſelf in ſomething elſe; and when this mind is up, then it's eaſie for the Enemy to come and enter in with his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements and Allurements, to entangle the mind, and lead the Creature into the Cloud of Error; and in that thing to which the Creature hath been moſt addicted, will the Enemy moſt appear, to bring it into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, which when it riſes, if it be ſavoured or liked, the Enemy hath his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to enſnare: But the Virgin-Seed delights in God alone, and is throughly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the enjoyment of the preſence of God the Lord, and this is that in which the Judgment ſtands, and the Power which wil
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38351:49"/>keep out of the ſnare of the wicked, unto which all muſt come before ye can grow into the plenteous Redemption, &amp; be made Heirs of Eternal Salvation, &amp; the Bleſſings of his Peace, which eſtabliſhes man in his growth and livelineſs, to grow up as the Corn in the night ſeaſon, and to be like the Trees bringing forth their pleaſant fruits, which who brings them forth, becomes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and receives confidence in God; but ſuch as bring not forth the pleaſant fruits, that which ſhould be their encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement becomes their Judge, and rejects them in their purpoſes, and ſo the growth in the Life they fall ſhort of.</p>
            <p>And all ye ſons and daughters, ye young men and women in whom the Virgin-Seed is ariſen, which delighteth in God, and hath its full delight in God, in which the Power &amp; Life ſtands to keep unſpotted of the world; it's ſafe for us to keep in Union with the Virgin, for ſhe is the Lambs Wife, and maketh her ſelf ready for the appearing of the Lamb, unto whom we have joyned in our youth, and ſhe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Wife of our youth; therefore let none deal treacherouſly with the Wife of his youth, but let the Virgin-Seed have the flower of her dayes in delighting her ſelf in God, and in doing his Will; I ſay, let none do violence to his Virgin, but dwell in Unity with her, and to be delighted in God with her, and to make ready with her, that all may be prepared againſt the Lamb comes; for he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecteth</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
